<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogmarks (Posts about mastodon)</title><link>https://chris48s.github.io/blogmarks/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://chris48s.github.io/blogmarks/categories/mastodon.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 chris48s</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 18:00:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>relay.fedi.buzz</title><link>https://chris48s.github.io/blogmarks/posts/2023/relay-fedi-buzz/</link><dc:creator>chris48s</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I self-host my own mastodon instance. I am &lt;a href="https://fed.chris-shaw.dev/@chris"&gt;the only user on my server&lt;/a&gt; and I only follow a handful of accounts. This means I inhabit a somewhat weakly connected corner of the fediverse. For example, following a tag doesn't act as a useful way for me to discover new posts because it almost exclusively shows me posts from people I am already following, which I know about anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a problem that is theoretically solved by ActivityPub Relays, although practically I was never really able to get a handle on which (if any) made sense for me to add to my instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That changed recently when I found out about &lt;a href="https://relay.fedi.buzz/"&gt;relay.fedi.buzz&lt;/a&gt; which allows you to generate ad-hoc follow-only ActivityPub relays for specific tags or instances (the most useful of those being tags IMO). For example, if I want to follow the &lt;code&gt;#python&lt;/code&gt; tag, I can add &lt;a href="https://relay.fedi.buzz/tag/python"&gt;https://relay.fedi.buzz/tag/python&lt;/a&gt; to my instance's relays. That ingests a much wider range of posts featuring that tag into my federated timeline, including from instance I was not already federated with via my follows. Then following that tag from my personal account now allows me to discover new posts on that topic.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>mastodon</category><guid>https://chris48s.github.io/blogmarks/posts/2023/relay-fedi-buzz/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>